welcome back to another edition of
disability insurance law TV my name is
Gregory Dell and I'm a long term
disability insurance attorney today I'm
joined by attorney Cesar Gaviria and
attorney Stephen Jessup we work with the
law firm of attorneys Dell and Shaffer
and in today's episode we are going to
discuss the Prudential Insurance Company
we do these videos on a weekly basis to
give you an idea of the way that these
long term disability insurance companies
are handling your long term disability
claim in anticipation of today's video I
did a little bit of research on
Prudential Insurance Company so that you
can have an idea of how big of a company
Prudential is Prudential is what they
claim to be the second largest group
insurance company in the entire world
they currently have over 42,000
employees their revenues last year were
thirty two point six eight six eight
eight billion dollars so that's thirty
two billion six hundred and eighty eight
million in revenues and just recently in
the last quarter their profits were six
hundred and ninety seven million now
Prudential does all kinds of insurance
products but more specifically just last
quarter their group insurance division
which includes long term disability had
fifty three million dollars in profits
so Prudential is a very large and very
powerful disability insurance company
now to prepare for today we've pulled
some specific cases around the country
regarding Prudential we're also going to
talk to you about some of our own cases
that we've handled against Prudential
including a pending class action that we
recently filed against Prudential but I
want to start first with Cesar Gaviria
who I think you're going to talk about a
recent case in which there was a
substantial verdict against Prudential
for their wrongful handling of a
long-term disability claim yes this this
particular case involved a project
manager who worked in this construction
department of University of California
San Francisco and she had developed
chronic fatigue syndrome lupus and
fibromyalgia and had filed a disability
claim with Prudential Prudential
approved her for about six years and
then terminated her benefits they also
denied all levels of Appeal that she
that she tried to execute the plaintiff
in this particular case then sued
Prudential for breach of contract and
bad-faith alleging that the insurance
company wrongfully terminated her
benefits and very you see this
particular thing very rarely she also
sued the independent company that set up
the imes for Prudential and sued the IME
doctor well the jury found that
Prudential not only breached the
contract but acted in bad faith awarded
about almost fifteen million dollars in
back benefits punitive damages and other
damages as well what they were really I
think intensified over was the fact that
Prudential never contacted her friends
or family any of her core workers to get
any of the information about her
condition or daily activities and they
just denied the claim based off of this
independent reported independent medical
doctor who just gave them the opinion
they wanted to hear and you said that
this jury was able to award fifteen
million dollars well they awarded
fifteen million but then later on the
appeals court knocked it down to four
million in punitive damages
they let stand some of the attorneys
fees they let stand the back benefits
that she was paid but either way was I
think a big wake-up call to Prudential
and Prudential always rights group
disability insurance policies but if
this policy this particular claim went
to a jury trial and
so their claims are governed by ERISA
how did that happen well this particular
claimant worked for as I said the
University of California which is a
state-run university under ERISA there
are certain types of disability plans
that are exempt for instance any
governmental entities any Church plans
any plans that are self-funded from the
general assets of the company those are
the type that are exempted from ERISA
and you could actually bring state law
causes of actions for him okay so if
this claim if the particular claim that
you're talking about was governed by
ERISA then there would be no ability to
bring a claim for punitive damages or
bad faith right you wouldn't be able to
bring aside from perhaps a claim for
attorneys fees that is granted on within
the courts discretion they may decide to
do it and they may decide not to award
it you can't bring any of the other bad
faith causes of action or any of those
things well I certainly hope that
$15,000,000 sent a message to Prudential
that their wrongful terminations won't
be tolerated Steve what kind of case did
you come across you know it's funny like
Cesar and I and a lot of calls that we
do take I found a case here a person
insured was a florist person at the
Mohegan Sun Casino and there was another
case of fibromyalgia and chronic fatigue
this one had been out of Connecticut of
course
Prudential shoots down the case and
there's no objective evidence of the
condition and that's one of the things
that the insurance companies you'll see
a lot of Prudential especially with
subjective they say it's all subjective
complaint of being sure that you can't
verify interesting here and it gives
maybe a little glimmer of hope for
people in Connecticut the Second Circuit
Federal District this is actually really
favorable here where the court comes out
and says because fibromyalgia does not
outwardly manifest itself it would be
unreasonable to require objective
evidence to support a diagnosis of
fibromyalgia however the court even goes
so far and is people suffering from
fibromyalgia we'll know the trigger
point test where the doctor is going to
you know check eighteen certain points
on your body they said here on your for
the Second Circuit federal court that
that trigger point testing if you come
up with 11 of the 18 is concrete proof
its objective evidence of the condition
the court then went to going into how
their doctors reviewed the case about
not so much looking as what was in the
medical records what the complaints were
but we're pointing to certain things
that weren't there loss of range of
motion or functional strength that
weren't even you know usual normal
symptoms of the condition itself and
it's funny because even today I looked
over a denial letter a Prudential denial
letter for a case that we took a call on
the earliest week and I couldn't help
but laugh to myself because everything
that the court was attacking Prudential
on I'm reading this denial letter and
everything this denial letter is what
they wrote in this denial letter for the
most part that the court ripped apart
saying how can you require this of it so
it's just amazing how there's always a
running theme and even though in this in
the case these are discussed where you
have a large verdict against them it's
like they don't learn from their
mistakes they figure I will just keep
doing it because we're sure not not that
many people really fight us well you
know it's I heard you say in your case
easer average Steve I heard you say it
as well this objective evidence it's
like Prudential is obsessed with trying
to look for objective evidence and their
claims handling people are trained to
say well you don't have any objective
evidence so we don't think you're
disabled well the reality is that you
don't have to have positive findings on
an MRI or an x-ray or a blood test or a
cat scan or something like that in order
to be disabled and Prudential has been
told hundreds if not thousands of times
by courts across the country that you
can't deny every single claim because
there is an objective evidence and the
sad thing is is that especially with
orthopedic let's say spinal conditions
the statistics are especially from a
recent study out of Harvard that 85% of
the people who go to doctor with with
some kind of spinal complaint the
doctors can't tell you the exact
objective cause of that condition that
doesn't mean that you don't have the
pain that you're saying you have so you
need to be able to work with your
treating physicians to be able to show
what your restrictions or limitations
are even if you don't have strong
objective evidence